# **ESTHER SANDERS**

## SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

804.901.4165

esthernaomi.violin@gmail.com

https://www.linkedin.com/in/esthersanders23/

https://github.com/esthersanders

https://esthersanders.github.io/

#### **ABOUT**

I've worked as a violinist and teacher for over a decade and was drawn to software development because of the many similarities to music. I love learning, continually refining skills, problem solving, and attention to detail. I have many years of experience self starting, dissecting large problems into smaller parts, and communicating complex ideas.

#### **TECHNICAL EXPERIENCE**

## Nashville Software School

NSS is a six-month intensive, full-time software development bootcamp focusing on HTML, CSS, Javascript, React and server-side fundamentals with Python and Django.

- Single-page dynamic application development with full CRUD functionality using React with a focus on modern ES6+ Javascript features and modular code
- Project management with issue tickets and GitHub Projects
- SCRUM framework to manage individual responsibilities and effective communication during group project sprints
- Database planning by building entity relationship diagrams (ERD) to define relationships with an emphasis on maintaining a flat data structure
- Managing HTTP requests with a backend server written in Python using Django ORM
- Querying a database with SQLLite in conjunction with Python
- Multiple full stack group and individual projects
- Styled applications using CSS, Bootstrap, reactstrap, Material UI, Grommet UI
- Completed 7 group project sprints while fully remote, comfortable with Slack, Zoom, GitHub Projects, and wireframes for group communication and collaboration

#### **PROJECTS**

#### Listen

Listen is a full stack application for musicians to get the most out of their practice time by recording themselves and setting goals. It also enables teachers to monitor their students' progress and practice habits. Built using React, JavaScript, Python, Django, CSS, SQLite, Grommet UI, and react-media-recorder.

Back End-https://github.com/esthersanders/listen-server

Front End-https://github.com/esthersanders/listen-client

### **BetterMe**

BetterMe is an app for users to create and track many habits simultaneously, with a visual representation of their progress. Built using the React framework for JavaScript, it also utilizes CSS, reactstrap, and Material UI. Information about the habits users create is stored using JSON server and includes full CRUD functionality.

https://github.com/esthersanders/BetterMe

#### **Group Project: Rare**

Rare is a social application for users to post and view articles. I worked with four other team members to create this full stack app using React, JavaScript, Python, Django, CSS, SQLite, and Grommet UI. https://github.com/NSS-Day-Cohort-42/rare-fakes-news

## **Group Project: Nutshell**

Nutshell is a social application for users to use to organize their daily tasks, events, news articles, and interact with other users. I worked with three other team members to create this app. My contributions include the Tasks component, the logout button, the New Friend Form, and the Alien themed CSS styling. https://github.com/esthersanders/nutshell-alien-abductees

#### **EXPERIENCE**

# Nashville Symphony / Section Violin

January 2012 - PRESENT, Nashville, TN

• Learn and perform new repertoire every week while quickly adapting to changes by listening and adjusting to colleagues in real time

# **Lipscomb University / Violin Instructor**

August 2020 - PRESENT, Nashville, TN

- Teaching individual private lessons to music majors
- Tailoring learning objectives, repertoire, and technical studies to each student's individual needs based on their past training and future goals
- Emphasizing the fundamentals of sound production and problem solving at every opportunity, in a variety of contexts, to encourage the transfer of important concepts to new situations
- Empowering students to be their own teacher by cultivating sharper listening skills to identify problems, then facilitating an awareness of how to solve problems through small steps

#### Musician/Teacher

2010-PRESENT

- Performed with many small and large ensembles as a section member (Austin Symphony, The Glimmerglass Festival) and as a leader (Austin Opera)
- Recording sessions for soundtracks, artists, bands
- Regularly record and perform while sight-reading (no prior rehearsals) or with minimal rehearsal
- Accustomed to working on a short timeline with a high level of focus
- Maintained a private violin studio of 20-30 students of all ages and levels. Responsibilities included scheduling, lesson planning, creating payment plans, implementing a studio policy to set expectations for students and parents, organizing student recitals at the end of each semester
- Instructor of violin at four colleges- Texas Lutheran University, Concordia University, Austin Community College, Lipscomb University. Individual and group lessons. Responsible for grades, repertoire choices, collaborating with other faculty, leading group classes with students at a wide variety of proficiency levels

#### **EDUCATION**

Nashville Software School / Full Stack Software Development July 2020-January 2021

The University of Texas at Austin / Master of Music, Violin Performance

Vanderbilt University / Bachelor of Music, Violin Performance